Guide to the John T. Wilson Papers 1930-1983
University of Chicago Library
Wilson, John Todd. Papers
1930-1983
4.5 linear feet (8 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The Wilson, John Todd. Papers consist of 4.5 linear feet of speeches and remarks, correspondence, certificates, published papers and book reviews, and Wilson's masters thesis and dissertation. Ninth president of the University of Chicago, Wilson was an expert on relations between universities and government. While provost he responded to economic pressures of inflation and cutbacks in government aid to education by implementing a five-year austerity plan. He was also noted for his fundraising efforts and as a supporter of student activities.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
John Todd Wilson was born on March 17, 1914, in Punxsutawney, Pennsylvania. He was one of nine children of Reverend Clark Wilson and Alice Warren. John Wilson received his A.B. degree with distinction from George Washington University in 1941, an M.A. in 1942 from the State University of Iowa, and a Ph.D. in psychology from Stanford University in 1948. He married Ann Camilli Wilson, his second wife, in 1939.
During World War II, Wilson served in the United States Naval Reserve. He was commissioned as an Ensign in 1942 and left the service as a Lieutenant Commander USNR in 1946.
In 1948, Wilson became Assistant Executive Secretary of the American Psychological Association while teaching concurrently as an Assistant Professor of Psychology at George Washington University. He returned to government service in 1950 as the head of the Personnel and Training Research Branch of the Office of Naval Research. He left the Office of Naval Research in 1952 for the newly created National Science Foundation, where he served as Program Director for Psychology in the Biological and Medical Sciences Division. In 1955, he became Assistant Director of NSF for Biological and Medical Sciences.
Wilson first came to the University of Chicago in 1961 as a special assistant to President George W. Beadle. He was also appointed as Professor of Psychology and taught graduate level courses. From 1963 to 1968 Wilson served as Deputy Director of the NSF and received the Foundation's first Distinguished Service Award.
Wilson returned to the University of Chicago in 1968 as Vice-President and Dean of Faculties. He became Provost in 1969 under President Edward H. Levi. While Provost, Wilson responded to the economic pressures of inflation and cutbacks in government aid to education by implementing a five-year austerity plan. He held the position of Provost until February 1975 when Levi resigned to become U.S. Attorney General. Wilson then became Acting President and expected to hold that position until a replacement was found. Although initially reluctant to accept the post, he was elected President by the Board of Trustees on December 9, 1975. He was noted for his fundraising efforts at a time of financial difficulty for all universities and as a supporter of student activities. He served as the ninth president of the University of Chicago until July 1, 1978, when he was succeeded by Hanna H. Grey.
Wilson was a noted expert on relations between universities and government. He was the author of Academic Science, Higher Education, and the Federal Government 1950-1983 (University of Chicago Press, 1983), Higher Education and the Washington Scene: 1963 and Higher Education and the Washington Scene: 1983 (University of Chicago Press, 1963 and 1982). Wilson was also the author of numerous articles on psychology and human learning, personnel selection and training, and research programming and administration. He was the co-author of Current Trends in Psychology and Behavioral Sciences (University of Pittsburgh Press, 1954).
Wilson continued teaching at the university until 1984. He died on August 4, 1990, at the age of 76.
Scope Note
The Wilson, John Todd. Papers consist of 4.5 linear feet of speeches and remarks, correspondence, certificates, published papers and book reviews, and Wilson's masters thesis and dissertation. The information in the papers covers the period from 1930 to 1983 and has been arranged into five series: (1) Personal, (2) Writings, (3) National Science Foundation, (4) University of Chicago, and (5) Oversize. Each series has been arranged chronologically.
Series I, Personal, includes bound copies of Wilson's master's thesis and Ph.D. dissertation as well as family genealogy notes written in 1982. Certificates and honorary degrees bestowed on Wilson between 1940 and 1979 are also included in the first series. Series V, Oversize, includes additional certificates and degrees.
Series II, Writings, has been subdivided into two subseries: (1) Published Papers and (2) Book Reviews. The Published Papers include articles written by Wilson between 1943 and 1983. One highlight of this subseries is an original roundtable transcript from the University of Chicago Roundtable program in December 1967. The Book Reviews include reviews written by Wilson between 1947 and 1979.
Series III contains speeches and remarks from his term of office at the National Science Foundation. The material covers the period 1959-1968. This series has been subdivided into two subseries: (1) Speeches and Remarks and (2) Congressional Committee Statements. Subseries 2 also includes speeches and remarks made by Wilson as Assistant Director of the National Science Foundation for Biological and Medical Sciences before United States Congressional committees between 1966 and 1979. Among the items in this series are remarks for a presentation before the National Conference on Title VI-Civil Rights Act of 1964.
Series IV contains speeches, remarks, and some correspondence from Wilson's term of office as Provost and then President of the University of Chicago. The material covers the period 1969 to 1983. This series has been subdivided into two subseries: (1) Provost and President Speeches and (2) Correspondence.
The second subseries contains letters of appreciation received between 1975 and 1981, including congratulations on being elected President of the University.
Series V contains oversized materials. The items in this series include diplomas from Wilson's high school, his B.A. degree from George Washington University, and a membership certificate for the American Academy of Arts and Sciences.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Wilson, John Todd, 1914-
National Science Foundation
University of Chicago-President
University of Chicago-Administration
University of Chicago-Provost
Psychology
Higher education and state-United States-History
INVENTORY
- Series I: Personal
  - Subseries 1: Thesis & Dissertation
    - Master's Degree Thesis - The University of Iowa - "Remote Associations as a Function of the Length of Interval Between Learning and Recall, " (Bound copy), July 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Doctoral Dissertation - Stanford University - "The Formation and Retention of Remote Associations in Rote Learning, " (Bound copy), June 1948; a congratulatory letter from Ben Underwood concerning the dissertation, August 28, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 2: Certificates
    - University of Chicago - to Ann Wilson (wife) - undated; State University of Iowa, M.A. degree, 1942; Honorary degree, Washington and Jefferson University, 1964 (?), Election to Society of Sigma XI (Science Research National Fraternity), 1948; Election to Sigma XI, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Fellow at the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, May 9, 1973; George Washington University, Junior Certificate, 1940; Ph.D. degree, Stanford University, 1948; University Record degree, August 7, 1973 (just a gag); George Washington University Alumni Achievement Award, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Honorary degree-Doctor of Humane letters - University of Chicago, June 15, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 3: Miscellaneous
    - Family genealogy notes, June 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Writings
  - Subseries 1: Published Papers
    - "Remote Associations as a Function of the Length of Interval Between Learning and Recall, " Journal of Experimental Psychology, July 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - A Review of General Semantics, Volume V, No. 1, Autumn1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Effect of an Increasingly Well-Defined Criterion on the Prediction of Success at Naval Training School (Tactical Radar)" (With Dewey B. Stuit), Journal of Applied Psychology, December 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "The Formation and Retention of Remote Associations in Rote Learning, " Journal of Experimental Psychology, December, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Personnel and Training Research in the Office of Naval Research, " Monthly Research Report, Office of Naval Research, February, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Psychology and the National Science Foundation, " The American Psychologist, September 1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Government Support on Research and its influence on Psychology, " The American Psychologist, December, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Government Support of Psychological Research, " (with Marguerite L. Young), The American Psychologist, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Remote Associations, "1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Fiscal Year, 1954, " (with Marguerite Young), The American Psychologist, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Psychology and Behavioral Science, " Current Trends in Psychology and the Behavioral Sciences, March 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Fiscal Year, 1955, " (with Marguerite Young) The American Psychologist, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Fiscal Year, 1956, " (with Marguerite Young) The American Psychologist, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Institutional Versus Individual Grantees, " from New York University Conference on Charitable Foundations1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Fiscal Year, 1957, " (with Marguerite Young), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Support of Research by NSF, " AIBS Bulletin, December, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Regional learning Research Centers, " in Operational Plans for Developing Regional Educational Media Research Centers, February 1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1963, " Educational Record, April 1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Human Values and Science, " Proceedings of the Third Annual Southeastern Michigan Junior Science and Humanities Symposium 1967, Wayne State University, Detroit Michigan, March 1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "The Effect of Government Policy on Research, " Julian Goldsmith, Robert Gomer, John T. Wilson, and Kenneth J. Northcott, WTTG Television, Channel 11, Chicago, The University of Chicago Roundtable, (original roundtable transcript)December 10, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - The Support of Individuals and Fields versus the Support of Individuals, " MINERVA, April 1971 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "The Threat to Private Colleges, " Christian Science Monitor, June 20, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1982, " (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1950 - 1983" (bound) 1983 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Subseries 2: Book Reviews
    - "Granville Stanley Hall, " (rough and final drafts), January 23, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "William James on Education, "February 11, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "L.L. Thurstone's "The Nature of Intelligence" (1924), March 3, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "Experimental Psychology, " by B.A. Farrell, in Personnel Administration, November 1955 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Present-Day Psychology, " A.A. Roback, Personnel Administration, March - April 1956 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "The Integrity of the Body, " by F.M. Burnet, The American Scholar, Oct. 1, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "The Effects of Federal Programs on Higher Education, " by Harold Orlans, March 7, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Their Psychological World, " by Bernice T. Eiduson, American Sociological Review, January 16, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - The Managerial Revolution in Higher Education, " by Francis E. Rourke and Glenn E. Brooks, Science, March 3, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "The Government of Science, " Harvey Brooks, Science, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Science and the Federal Patron, " by Michael D. Reagan, Science, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "Scholars, Dollars, and Bureaucrats, " by Chester E. Finn, Minerva, April 1979 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "American Higher Education, 1945 - 1970 - A Personal Report, " by Nathan M. Pusey, in American Journal of Education, November, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series III: National Science Foundation
  - Subseries 1: Speeches and Remarks
    - "The Principles and Applications of the Research Grant System, " Meetings of the Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology, Atlantic City, NJ, April 13, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "The National Science Foundation and the Academic Community, " 77th Annual Conference of the Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges, Chicago, Illinois, November, 13, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - "The Executive Office Complex and its Influence in the Governance of Research and Development Programs, " AAAS Meeting, Cleveland, Ohio, December 28, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "Hast any Philosophy in Thee, Shepherd?" Commencement Address, Washington and Jefferson College, Washington, Pennsylvania, June 6, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Remarks for Presentation before the National Conference on Title VI - Civil Rights Act of 1964, January 28, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Remarks...on the occasion of the dedication of the research vessel Eastward, Duke University Marine Laboratory, Beaufort, N.C., May 1, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - 1966, " Dedication of the new Psychology Department quarters, University of Chicago, January 19, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Some consideration of Federal support for higher education, its purposes and its effects, " Meeting of the National Association of College and University Attorneys, Princeton University, June 23, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Remarks...on the occasion of the dedication of the Physiology building, Naples Zoological Station, August 30, 1966 (Xerox) (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Remarks...on the occasion of the dedication of the New Science Building at Furman University, Greenville, S.C., October 22, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Remarks...to the National Council of University Research Administrators, Washington, D.C., December 1, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Remarks to the Eastern Association of College and University Business Officers, December 5, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Remarks...At the science conference on "The future of Science in the Liberal Arts Colleges, " Wheaton College, April 15, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "Science and Human Values, " Groundbreaking luncheon for the New Science Building, Maryville College, Maryville, Tennessee, May 29, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Background Paper for discussion of Departmental-level research and training support, at the joint meeting of NSB Committees I and III and NSB Meeting, September 6 and 8, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Remarks...on the Occasion of the Annual Meeting of the Academic Council of the National Association of State Universities and Land Grant Colleges - Columbus, Ohio, November 13, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Alan T. Waterman, All Souls' Church, Washington, D.C., December 4, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "Quo Vadis, " Meeting of the National Association of Biology Teachers, Anaheim, California, March 1, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Remarks...Michigan State Sigma Xi Lecture, East Lansing, Michigan, April 11, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2: Congressional Committee Statements
    - Subcommittee on Research and Technical Programs, House Committee on Government Operations - on International Science Activities (Reuss), February, 10, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Subcommittee on Intergovernmental Relations of the Senate Committee on Government Operations - on S.Res. 68, A Resolution to Establish a Senate Select Committee on Technology and Human Environment (Muskie), March 20, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Subcommittee on Economic Progress, Joint Economic Committee (Proxmire), April 21, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Paper for House Subcommittee on Science Research and Development - Federal Government Policies and Academic Science, July 20, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Subcommittee on Science, Research, and Technology, Committee on Science and Technology - House - (Brown), August 15, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series IV: University of Chicago
  - Subseries 1: Provost and President Speeches
    - Stochastics - Federal Government Policies and Academic Science, May 20, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Talk to Medical School Alumni - The University of Chicago, March 5, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Comments on the University to the leadership conference, May 8, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - University's1970 - 1971 budget, July 31, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Board Presentation -1971 - 1972 academic budget, March 6, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Federal Government Policies, The University and Academic Science, April 2, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - University's1971 - 1972 budget, September 7, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - University's1972 - 1973 budget, October 2, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Introductory Statement to Trustees, April 27, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Trustees Meeting, April 28, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - University's1973 - 1974 budget, October 1, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - University's1974 - 1975 budget, October 15, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar, April 22, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - University's1975 - 1976 budget, September 1, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Remarks on the Occasion of the visit of the Empress of Japan, October 7, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Remarks at dinner honoring Baron Ramsey of Canterbury, October 13, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Remarks at the luncheon for the King of Norway, October 16, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - ABA Dinner Scenario, October 17, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - State of the University (from The University Record), November 11, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "A Thousand Years Hence, "January 7, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Commercial Club of Chicago - "The Situation at the University of Chicago", February 11, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Remarks at the Lasker Dinner, February 11, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Installation of JTW as ninth President of the University; plus The University Record (April 3, 1976);March 4, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Remarks at the dedication of the Al Weisman Corner, April 7, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - King of Sweden Toast, April 19, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Remarks following dinner of Library Visiting Committee, April 20, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Philip B. Kurland, April 27, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Remarks at the luncheon at the Ritz - Carlton - "The University and the City, "April 29, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Remarks on the occasion of the Jefferson Lecture (John Hope Franklin), May 5, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Remarks on the occasion of the inaugural lecture by the first Helen Ross Professor - Margaret Rosenheim, May 6, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Remarks on the occasion of the Lying-In dinner, May 26, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Remarks at the President's Fund dinner, June 2, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Remarks on the occasion of the groundbreaking for the renovation of the Henry Crown Fieldhouse, June 3, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Remarks at the Order of the "C" Banquet (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - "Historic Impression" - WEFM two-minute talk, plus correspondence, June 25, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Remarks on the occasion of the visit of the Osaka Chamber of Commerce, July 5, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Introduction - 100th Woodward Court Lecture (John Hope Franklin), October 26, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - State of the University (from The University Record), November 9, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - NEH Dinner - Ronald Berman, November 17, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Nobel Laureate Dinner, December 3, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Trustee-Faculty dinner - "Telegraph Stagg for Plans", January 12, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - President's Report - Council Meeting (Browder Affair), 1976 - 1977 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - President's Report - Council Meeting (Browder Affair), 1976 - 1977 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - President's Report - Council Meeting (Browder Affair), 1976 - 1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Remarks on the Occasion of the Jefferson Lecture (Saul Bellow), April 1, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Introduction of Robert Streeter - Fourth Ryerson Lecture, April 5, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Remarks on the Occasion of the Tut Dinner, April 12, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Remarks at the dinner opening the Conference on the Jewish Religious Tradition, April 17, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Message to Alumni, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Remarks on the occasion of the Mother's Aid luncheon, October 5, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Remarks to leadership conference, October 13, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Remarks at the luncheon for HRH Prince Charles, October 19, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Remarks - President's Fund Dinner, October 26, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Remarks on the occasion of the Joint Negro Appeal Banquet (John Hope Franklin), October 30, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - State of the University (from The University Record), November 8, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Dedication to the Fieldhouse (Henry Crown), November 1, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Introductory Remarks at the Biological Sciences Civic Dinner (Dr. John H. Knowles), November 14, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Remarks at the Dedication of the Surgery-Brain Research Pavillion, November 15, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Trustee-Faculty Dinner - Remarks on the College, January 11, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Memo to Faculty - Office of Civil Rights, January 30, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Memo to Faculty - Office of Civil Rights (May 8, 1978), March 10, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Introduction of Albert Dorfman - Ryerson Lecture (Fifth), March 29, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Medical Feasibility Study, April 26, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Remarks by "Jock" Weintraub and Philip Kurland, May 24, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Editorial - The Christian Science Monitor, June 20, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Heinrich Klüver Memorial Remarks, March 27, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Statement of NSF to House Subcommittee on Science, Research and Technology, September 10, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - 1980, November 27, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Remarks to society of Research Administrators on History of NSF, October 6, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Letter to L. Branscomb, Chairman of National Science Board, April 27, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Remarks at Gaylord Donnelly Dinner, November 12, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Remarks on Science Education - Academy on education, October 14, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Remarks in tribute to Allison Davis, October 21, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2: Correspondence
    - Letters of Appreciation, 1975 - 1981 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
- Series V: Oversize
  - The George Washington University, Degree of Bachelor of Arts (with Distinction), June 11, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Membership degree to the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, May 9, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Punxsutawney High School Diploma, Punxsutawney, Pa., June 6, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 3)